<!-- <?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
               "/usr/share/sgml/docbook/dtd/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY fdictUrl "http://www.freedict.org">
<!ENTITY fdictMail " freedict-beta@lists.sourceforge.net" >
<!ENTITY MichEmail "bunk@imn.htwk-leipzig.de" >
<!ENTITY PeteEmail  "petergozz@users.sf.net">

<!ENTITY fdl SYSTEM "fdl.xml">
<!ENTITY gpl SYSTEM "gpl.xml">
<!ENTITY writing SYSTEM "writing.xml">
<!ENTITY requirements  SYSTEM "requirements.xml">
 ]> -->

<chapter id="requirements">
  <title>Basic Requirements</title>
  <abstract>
    <para>This chapter describes the <indexterm><primary>basic requirements</primary></indexterm>
      basic requirements for inclusion in the FreeDict project.
      Before we can accept a dictionary for inclusion in the FreeDict project, we
      ask that it meets a common set of specifications. This section gives an overview 
      of those requirements. Essentially, a dictionary must meet clear
      copyright and licensing guidelines and must be presented in a particular XML format.</para>
  </abstract>

  <section id="Licensing">
    <title>Licensing and <indexterm><primary>Copyright</primary></indexterm>Copyright</title>
    <para>The FreeDict project including all content, documentation and tools is
      <indexterm><primary>Free Software</primary></indexterm>Free Software. Any dictionary
      to be considered for archiving and release by this project must first be Free, Open Source
      Software.</para>
    <para>The developers of a dictionary may always hold the copyright to their particular
      dictionary. There are a number of available licenses that can readily achieve this for you.</para>
    <para>This means you must release the dictionary under the terms and conditions of the GNU
      General Public License (GPL Version 2 or later),  or a License of
      <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/license-list.html">compatible type</ulink>.</para>
    <para>Alternatively you may formally release the dictionary to the
      <indexterm><primary>public domain</primary></indexterm>Public Domain. You should understand
      that in doing so you have no easy way of stopping anybody from capturing your content and
      locking it up under their own Copyright and/or License. We don't recommend this.</para>
    <para>We do recommend the <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html">GPL Version 2</ulink>
      or the <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html">GNU Free Documentation License</ulink>.
      Of course it's your choice. Both of these licenses (and those that are compatible with them),
      protect you and your Copyright. Briefly; they say you are releasing the dictionary:<simplelist>
	<member>1/ In the hope that it will be useful,</member>
	<member>2/ With no warranty to it's fitness or otherwise for any use, and</member>
	<member>3/ You allow free use and access to the work, provided the user passes on the same
          right if any substantial part of the work is included in their own.</member></simplelist></para>
   
    <para>Please understand that FreeDict will not agree to any license that does not meet or agree
      with the aims and scope of the GPL2<indexterm><primary>GPL2</primary></indexterm>. For current
      examples of licenses that do agree (and some that don't), please see:
      <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/license-list.html">http://www.gnu.org/licenses/license-list.html</ulink>.</para>
    
  </section>

  <section id="tei-xml">
    <title>XML Markup</title>
    <para>FreeDict dictionaries are marked up using the XML version of the
	<ulink url="http://www.tei-c.org/">Text Encoding Initiative</ulink> DTD,
	Chapter 12 (Dictionaries).</para>
    <para>This may seem a little daunting at first, but please read on as we are
	working quickly to make this much easier. Full instructions are given in
	the "<link linkend="writing">Writing A Dictionary</link>" section.
	We are also developing and testing <link linkend="tools">tools</link>
	that may be suitable for automating most of this. 
      <indexterm>
	<primary>Text Exchange Initiative</primary>
	<secondary>TEI DTD</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </para>

    <para>There are many advantages to using a standard content based approach
	like this:</para>

    <orderedlist numeration="upperroman">
      <title>Advantages of using the TEI XML markup format</title>
      <listitem>
	<para>Inherits most of the advantages of XML including:
	 <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	   <para>content based rather than layout based</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	   <para>application independent</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>platform independent</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>further processing readily possible across the entire FreeDict collection</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>enables full use of existing or customised XML technologies</para>
          </listitem>
	 </itemizedlist>
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Standardises input and output formats.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Protects against obsolescence</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>TEI has comprehensive DTDs available.
	 <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The Dictionary DTD is just one of a very wide conceptual set.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Elements already exist for lexicographic, etymological, phonetic
		and other particularities of dictionaries.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The TEI XML combination allows processing, development and use
		 beyond the immediate scope of the FreeDict translating dictionaries.</para>
	  </listitem>
	 </itemizedlist>
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>TEI technologies are reasonably well understood and used in academic circles.</para>
      </listitem>
      
    </orderedlist>

    <section id="Unicode">
      <title>The Universal Character Set (UCS)</title>
<formalpara id="Unicode-howto">
	<title>From the Unicode How To</title>
	<para>  
	  <quote> People in different countries use different characters to represent the words of their native languages. Nowadays most applications, including email systems and web browsers, are 8-bit clean, i.e. they can operate on and display text correctly provided that it is represented in an 8-bit character set, like ISO-8859-1. </quote><citation>Bruno Haible: Linux Unicode Howto</citation> <indexterm>
	    <primary>Bruno Haible</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
	    <primary> Unicode</primary></indexterm></para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
   <title> What is Unicode?</title>
      <para>From:<citation><ulink url=" http://www.unicode.org/standard/WhatIsUnicode.html" id="link-unicodeOrg"> http://www.unicode.org/standard/WhatIsUnicode.html </ulink></citation>
	<literallayout>
	<quote>Unicode provides a unique number for every character,
	    no matter what the platform,
	    no matter what the program,
	    no matter what the language.</quote>
	  </literallayout>
	 
      </para></formalpara>
      <para>Essentially, Unicode encoding  supplies the unique character number that is typed to the page each time you enter a letter on your keyboard. A font-set then renders the character onto the screen so that you may read it. It's important to understand that Unicode is not a font-set, it is a protocol for the mappings that font-sets use to render fonts on your screen or on to a printed page.</para>
      <highlights>
	<tip>
	  <para>All new dictionaries should be written using a Unicode  UTF-8
compatible character set. If you use a text editor with a simple UTF-8 compliant font all should be well.</para>
	  <para> UTF-8 is a very clever way of wrapping up all of the commonly used Latin and non Latin character sets in a portable efficient way. This includes most 8 bit and many<emphasis> 16bit or 2 byte</emphasis> character sets. Your current character sets are probably included, so it may be as simple as putting &lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?&gt; as the XML declaration of your final document.</para></tip></highlights>
<para>You should ensure that your Dictionary does not rely on any particular font set and is equally functional when rendered as simple text. Remember fonts are just "pretty renderings" of real characters. Most modern Text Editors ( e.g. Xemacs,emacs, Vim, GEdit, Kedit, notepad) should be fine.</para>
      <para>This is not the place for a full explanation of Unicode. Please see Markus Kuhn's excellent summary at<ulink url="http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~mgk25/unicode.htm" id="link-utf8"> http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~mgk25/unicode.htm</ulink>. The Linux Unicode HOWTO is  well worth visiting e.g. <ulink url="ftp://ftp.ilog.fr/pub/Users/haible/utf8/Unicode-HOWTO.html">ftp://ftp.ilog.fr/pub/Users/haible/utf8/Unicode-HOWTO.html</ulink><indexterm>
	  <primary>encoding</primary>
	  <secondary>UTF-8</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Web Browsers</primary>
	  <secondary>Unicode Compliance</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>Universal Character Set</primary>
	  <secondary> UCS-2</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>UTF-8</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary>ISO IEC</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
	  <primary> ISO 10646</primary> <secondary>ISO</secondary>
	</indexterm>

  </para>
     
      <itemizedlist spacing="normal" id="uft8quick">
	<title>UTF-8 Quick notes</title>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The<emphasis> Universal Character Set</emphasis> is defined by<emphasis> ISO/IEC standard ISO 10646</emphasis>.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para> Unicode is a parallel standard that functionally defines a few "coal face" or real life, protocols.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Unicode is kept in synchronisation with ISO/IEC 10646.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para> UTF-8 is one of some four formal definitions of Unicode. The other common one is UTF-16.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem> 
	  <para>Please don't use a UTF-16 based font unless you have no other choice.</para>	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>UTF-8 covers most common 16 bit character sets as well. (through some clever "flags" at the font of the character.)</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>UTF-8 is the default standard for XML documents and is an excellent choice as it contains the character mappings sets from (almost) all known languages, while being fully compliant with current and earlier computer standards. Note most web browsers and protocols assume a UTF-8 compliant encoding</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>All ISO type character sets in general use are covered by UTF-8 (including ASCII) as are the KJC Family.(Korean, Japanese and some of the Chinese family of characters.) Broadly speaking you should not have a problem with this. If your editor has a UTF-8 option please set it on.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <tip>
	<para>If you have automated some or all of your dictionary construction please be careful to maintain character type compatibility throughout the process. C coders should use the <quote>wide character type</quote>. Most scripting languages now also support UTF-8.( Python, Perl, PHP, Java and  Ruby at least.). Shell scripts usually adopt the local environment settings.  Please check your Gawk and SED are mapping  cleanly. You may need very recent versions. 
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Scripting Languages</primary>
	    <secondary>Python, Perl, Java, PHP, Ruby</secondary>
	    <tertiary>Awk Sed Sh ENV</tertiary>
	  </indexterm>
	</para>
      </tip>
      <formalpara id="Unicode-more">
	<title>More Information</title>
	<para>If your on a Linux (or similar) system try :
	  <command>man 7 unicode</command> for more information.  You
	  may also have some unicode tool(s) on board  <command>man 1
	    unicode</command>. You may also need to set your LANG environment settings, most Linux type systems support doing this on a per instance basis, that is you may run a number of language and locales concurrently. Examples are given later. Meantime <command>man 7 locale</command> and <command>man 1 locale</command>.<indexterm>
	    <primary>locale</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary> LANG</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	  <indexterm>
	    <primary>Linux Manual Page</primary>
	  </indexterm>
	</para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>Templates and examples are given in the <link linkend="examples">Examples Section</link></para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  </chapter>
